on this video we are going to take a
look at six new features that are coming
to JavaScript this year these new
features are part of the ekma 2023
specification which is the document that
specifies how JavaScript should work and
what features it has I like this year's
updates a lot because they help us write
codes that is more predictable has less
bugs and is easier to maintain that is
because array methods in JavaScript can
sometimes be confusing for example take
a look at this code X contains one two
and three then we have white whose value
is equals to X both reversed and finally
we are doing why that push adding 0 to Y
the final value of y is easy to know it
will be three two one zero which is the
reverse of X plus the zero we pushed at
the end now the question is what is the
final value of x choose option A
or option b the correct option is B
if we read the code again you could
think that X remains as 1 2 and 3
because it looks like we are only
working with Y since we assigned x dot
reverse to Y and then pushed 0 to Y and
not X but because the reverse method
does not create a new array and it
actually modifies the original array
that is called on which in this case is
X this means that X is reversed along
with Y then when we push zero onto y
it's like we are also pushing 0 onto X
because they are both references to the
same array even though by reading the
code it does not seem like it the code
has a box that will be hard to catch if
we are not aware that the reverse method
is mutating our program's State because
of these types of box there are many
programming languages like Haskell
clutcher Scala erlang and Rost among
many others that completely forbid or
discourage mutations those languages
don't allow you or or help you avoid
mutating a variable instead they make
you create a modified copy of the
original one mutations can lead to a
variety of books that are often hard to
spot and debug even react has this
concept if you are a react developer you
know that we should never mutate the
state we should always create a new one
to make things even worse JavaScript is
not really consistent on which methods
mutate and which methods don't for
example the sort method used to order an
array changes the array in place it
mutates it but the filter method used to
remove unwanted items from an array does
not mutate it it returns a copy because
mirability is okay in JavaScript you as
a developer have to remember which
methods mutate and which methods don't
and you also have to do the copying of
the arrays manually to avoid mutating
the state so to fix the problem with our
code we have to first copy X into y
making a whole new array and then we can
proceed to mutate or we can use the new
to reversed method that does not mutate
the array it returns a modified copy of
it so now our code can look like this
and it will be bug free apart from two
reverse we also have two sorted and two
spliced to sort it we'll sort an array
but unlike sort it will not mutate it it
will instead return a modified copy to
spliced is a bit different from the
original mutation loving splice let's do
a recap real quick using this price you
can delete items in an array starting
from a specific index so for example
here we have an array with four letters
and then we call splice the first
argument of splice tells it on which
index to start removing items in our
case we say index number one which means
the second item the second argument is
how many items to delete in our case we
say we want to remove two items so with
this code the b and c letters will be
removed splice will mutate the array in
place and it will return another array
with with the deleted items two splice
does not do this it does not mutate the
array and it does not return an array of
the deleted items it Returns the
modified copy of the original array
sometimes you want to know which items
were deleted so for this reason you
might want to keep using splice rather
than to splice if you don't need the
deleted items then moving to two splice
will keep your code immutable inside
effect free another Super useful new
method is wheat wheat allows you to
modify the item inside of an array
without mutating the original so for
example if we had this array and we
wanted to change the X for ad without
the new width method we would do
something like this but that would
mutate the original array instead we can
use the wheat method we will pass the
index of the item we want to change and
the new value and we will get a copy of
the original array with the modified
value and last but not least we have the
find last and find last in the index
methods they are a mirror to the already
existing find and find index methods
find will give you the first item on an
array that matches your search and you
find the index will give you the index
where that item is find the last and
find the last index work and look the
same way except that they search for the
last item and not the first one and
that's it for this video I hope you
found it useful and I hope that this new
method can help you make your code
better and reduce unexpected box in your
code I always get the questions of where
and how do these JavaScript updates get
decided who comes up with them and who
decides to implement them if that's
something you're curious about let me
know in the comments and I'll make a
video about how JavaScript is made also
let me know in the comments what your
favorite method is on this list and if
you have had any boxes view to mutations
before and please remember that you can
take our free JavaScript for beginners
course where we spend 8 hours learning
JavaScript together and where we build
things like clocks to-do lists weather
geology location and more to join just
click the link below and roll for free
and I will see you there alone
see you on the next one bye
foreign